So now we're going to look at some more patterns of the different things we can
do at the top of the loop, in the middle of the loop, and at the bottom of the
loop. And the first one we're going to do is counting. Now we're going to take a
look at the number of something, the number of things in our list. Now we
could just inspect it and see six, but you will have for loops, like you're
reading through a file, or you know, scanning through some data, and so the
notion of counting, you have to assume that you don't really know, you know, dot
dot dot dot dot, that there's going to be a lot more than just six. But for now
we're just going to do six, and we're going to count how many things that we
see in this loop. And the pattern is simple. You set a variable, zork, to zero
at the beginning. We often call this variable count in mnemonic. And now we're
going to run this loop six times, one, two, three, four, five, six, and each time
through we're just going to add one to zork. So zork start at zero, then it goes
one, two, three, four, five, six, and we're going to print it out. So, you know, we see
the nine and zork is one. See 41, zork is two. And then in it, zork is 16, when we
see the 15, four stops, and we print out afterwards. And this then is, six is then
the ultimate count that we got. So that's very, very simple. The pattern is that set
it to zero at the beginning, add one to it, and if you run that enough times, then
this is how many times that happened. And in a sense, it's how
many times this line ran, right? Sometimes you put this in an if statement, etc, etc, etc, okay?
Oops. Now, we can do the same thing to get a total. And the way the total works is
you compute a running total of the number of the items that you've seen so
far, and at the end the running total, in effect, becomes the total. Will you, a
better variable name for this would be like sum or total or something, but zork,
I'll use zork again. So you set zork to zero, and it starts up. The total we've
seen so far is indeed zero. And then we're going to run this one, two, three, four, five,
six times, and thing is going to be the iteration variable. It's going to take on the
successive values. And each time through, we're just going to take our running total
and add to it the thing we've seen. So we see nine, and the running total is nine.
We see 41, and the running total becomes 50. We see 12, the running total becomes 62.
We get a 3, it becomes 65, we get 74, running total is 139. How many more, how
many more are we going to see? We don't know. Could be a million. Could be one. Oh, it's
only one. We get a 15, our running total is 154. And what's true at any moment here
is the running total is right above what we've seen so far. Now, when we're done,
the for loop quits for us, and afterwards, 154 is indeed the total. So the running
total while we're in the loop, at the end of the loop, after the end of the loop, we
have the actual total. So it's not very difficult to convert this to the average
because we calculated the count, and we calculated the running total, and now
we're going to have the average by simply dividing those. Okay, so now this time
I've used mnemonic variables. Don't get confused by this. Mnemonic variables are
just friendly names I chose for you to read the code easier. I am not
communicating to Python in any way by naming this count and sum, but count and
sum is nice. Okay, so I set count to zero and sum to zero. Oh, go back up. I set
count to zero and sum to zero at the beginning, and the count is zero and the
sum is zero, and then I'm going to run this loop six times. One, two, three, four, five,
six, and each time value is the iteration variable. Every time I run
the loop, I count equals count plus one, sum equals sum plus value, so I have a
running count and a running total, and they show up here. One, two, three, four,
five, six, and then the running total, and then at some point the for loop, you know,
we do the last one and the for loop jumps out, and it divides six, 154 is the
count and running total, and then it divides the average sum over count. Okay, so
that's just, again, a pattern of something in the beginning, something in
the middle, something in the end. Another kind of thing we tend to do in loops is
we look for things, we hunt for things, and so this is where we have an if
statement inside of a loop, and of course I've created a silly simple thing. In
this code, I am looking for large values that are values that are greater than 20,
and again, don't think of this as just six numbers, but I'm looking for all the
values and I'm going to print them out. So, you know, it says before, it's going to run
this, nine, well if nine's greater than 20, it's false, so it goes back up, 41, true, so
it prints out 41, then goes back up, 12, false, goes back up, three, false, goes back
up, 74, true, so it runs this, so out comes that little print statement, goes back up,
and then 15 is the last one, and that's false, it goes back up, and the for says
we're done, and then we do afterwards, and so this is just the notion of having
an if statement inside of a for loop, where we're sort of picking, or choosing,
or selecting, or looking for something in a large set of things that we're looping
through. We can also say I want to know if a particular value is there, and so
we're going to use a Boolean variable, and we've talked about integer variables
like 1, 42, and then floating point variables like 98.6, and then string
variables like hello world, that have quotes in them. This is a for type, type,
a kind of variable. It's called a Boolean variable, and it only has two values.
It has true and false. Matter of fact, these if statements, they return Boolean
values, value equal equal three, that is returning a true or a false based on the
value of value. There's a mnemonic confusion there, right, what I'm using.
So I'm going to make a variable called found, and that's a decent name for
a variable, so don't get hung up on that, and I'm going to initially say found is
going to indicate to me whether or not I found a 3 in my list, and I'm going to start
before the loop starts, let's say false, cuz we haven't found anything yet, so
found equals false, and so at the beginning of the loop, found is false.
Before the loop starts, found is false, and now we're going to run this loop a bunch
of times. 9, is that true? No, skip. 41, is that true? Skip. 12, skip. Right, so 9, 41, 12,
and found has remained false because we haven't done anything to it, but now in
comes a 3, and this becomes true, so it runs this code, so found becomes true, and
then we print it, and you'll notice that when we see a 3, we get true, and then it
runs again, we get 74, it still false, 15, it still false, run, run, run, quit, and the
residual afterwards is true, and in fact, if you didn't know any of this, you don't
print that out, all you know is that afterwards, we loop through all those
things, and we know that there was a 3 in there. That's what we're doing, so we
searched all of them, we checked for 3s, when we found a 3, and you can see
basically that the found remains false until it flips to true, but then
there's nothing to set it back to false, there's nothing in this loop that's going to
set it back to false, so once it sort of catches the 3, then it remains true for
the rest of the loop, and then it just finds its way out. Now if you want to
think about it for a moment, ask yourself, how might we make this loop more efficient
by putting a statement right in here? Think about a way to, once you found it,
and it's true, there is sort of no reason to keep on going, so what would you put
there to perhaps make this loop to look for 3s, just to tell you whether or not
there was at least one 3 in there, how to make that more efficient, just think
about that. Okay, so now let's look back at the largest value that we started out
with, right, and so if you if you think about this, let's kind of give it a sort
of a rough rough look here. Largest so far is our kind of like a running total,
but it's our our hypothesis is the best large number, and we have this if
statement that says if the number we just see right now is greater than the
largest so far, then capture it, right, take whatever number we saw and capture
it, so when we see 9, it's better we capture it, we see a 41, it's better we
capture it, we don't capture this, we don't capture this, we capture the 74, and
we don't capture the 15, and that's how we do it, so you could think of this as
better. When the number we're looking at is greater than our working
hypothesis of the largest, we grab it because it's better, so this this line
right here is the grab line, grab it, okay, so then the question is how would you
modify this code to teach it to find the smallest value in this list of numbers?
Think of it as you have a starting number, you have a sort of what's better
in this grabbing notion, how could you do that? Take a look. Okay, so let's take a
look, so let's let's do a couple things, like the if you look at this if
statement that's better, well it's better now if the number is less than, so if
the if then but then we should probably change this to be smallest so far,
smallest so far, smallest so far, smallest so far, smallest so far, smallest so far,
right, matter of fact that's what this is, we've changed the word largest so far to
smallest so far, and we've changed the greater than to a less than, is that
going to fix it? I'll give you a second to look at it, pause if you need, is that going to
fix it? Is that going to find our smallest number? The answer is of course no, it's
not, so if we run this code, so we set the smallest so far to negative 1 and it
starts out negative 1, we run it and it's 9, is 9 less than negative 1? No, it's not,
so after we see a 9, the smallest so far is negative 1, now we're going to run 41, is
41 less than negative 1? No, it is not, so small so far still negative 1, as a matter
of fact it isn't the smallest so far anymore, just because we named it smallest
so far doesn't mean it is the smallest so far, it didn't work out so well, and so
you see that none of these, because they're never less than negative 1, do
anything and we claim that afterwards the smallest we've seen so far is
negative 1, and that is because of course negative 1 is smaller than any of the
numbers that we saw, so how could we fix this? Well, if we started the smallest so
far with some like arbitrary big number, then it'd be better, so if we made this
a hundred, whoops, come back, if we made this be like a hundred, that'd be good,
because the first time through the 9 would be less than a hundred, so we would
capture the 9 and then the rest of the loop would work just fine, but then what
if we didn't know that how big these numbers were, as a matter of fact the
largest so far wouldn't have worked if all the numbers were negative, think
about that, we just assumed they were positive and so we kind of wrote lazy
code that assumed all numbers are positive, that might not be a good
assumption depending on the numbers that you're dealing with, right, so maybe a
hundred's a good number to start with, or maybe like a thousand, or ten thousand, or
like some number with lots of zeros in it, how big should we make this? And the
answer is we're kind of solving this problem the wrong way, and the thing we
really want to do to solve the problem is to just accept the fact that if we're
looking for the smallest number so far, that the right hypothesis is the first
number, and if we just knew what that first number was, the 9, that would
either, that would, because it's the first number, we know that it's the both the
largest so far and the smallest so far as soon as you see the first number, but we
don't know here before the loop starts what that first number is, I mean you
can look at it but assume this is just data that's coming from somewhere else
and we don't know it until we start reading it, so we have to construct a
loop that deals with the fact that we want to capture the first value as our
hypothesis for smallest so far, so how do we do that? Let's take a look, so what we
do is we use yet another type, so we have integer, floating point, string, boolean
and now we have a thing called the None type, None type is a special marker in
that it only has one value, boolean has true and false, you know, floating point
has an infinite number values and integer has an infinite number values but
None type has one value, none, none is a constant, capital none is a constant, the
difference is is we can check to see if we have stored none, none is often used
to indicate emptiness, not non-existence because smallest doesn't exist
until we assign it but we're going to assign it to like a mark, a flag, a marker, some
way to say oh this is not even a number, it's nothing and so we're going to win, you
can do this, so that's like makes a variable called smallest and in it puts
none, it sticks it right in, it's not a string none, it's like a special type, okay,
so that actually captures the notion that before the loop starts the smallest
number that we've seen so far is none, we haven't seen any numbers, okay, so then
we come in and we have an if statement and we have a new operator called is, is
stronger than equal sign and so if smallest is none that becomes true, it
runs this case and so then what it does is it copies this first value which is
nine into smallest and so we see a nine and the smallest so far is nine which is
the first value and again we're assuming we don't know what the first value is
before the loop starts so we use the first iteration through the loop as the
moment where we capture that, okay, so smallest is the value and then we
print it and we go back up and now it runs again with 41, 41 is not none, none
is there's only one thing that's none so it is not equal to none, smallest is not
equal to none or is not none so this is false so it skips over here then it asks
the question is the value we're looking at 41 less than smallest, well smallest is
nine in this case and this is 41 so that's false so it skips that and goes
on so we see 41 we don't take it and then you can see that this will never
become true again, this is pretty much false for the rest of the iterations of
the loop, that's false for the rest of the iterations for the loop so it just is
going to run down here and ask this question and at some point we see a three and we
run this code we capture it we see 74 we don't capture it we see 15 we don't
capture it so then the for loop skips out at the end we have the smallest and
actually this would be a good technique for the largest as well because it
really is just a technique to put a marker in this variable so that we snag
that first number or first whatever as we read and parse through them so the
is and is not operators are very useful in Python you can think of them as like
the double equal sign they're asking a question and they're asking a question
and they return a true or you know blank is blank returns a true or false it is
stronger double equal says are these two can these are these things equal in type
and value so just as an example if I were to say is 0 equal to 0.0 it would
say yeah that's true but then if I says 0 is 0.0 that would be false so that's
because these two are the same value wise and these two are not the same type
wise so is is stronger than equals meaning that it demands equality in both
the type of the variable and the value of the variable and no conversion is
done and so that's just a very strong don't overuse is if you're dealing with
numbers or even strings use double equals don't use is because sometimes it
gets a little confusing so use is sparingly I tend to only use is on
Booleans and on None types I don't use is on integers and I don't use in use is on
floats and I don't use is on strings just none or true false and also is not
is also an operator so you just say blah blah blah is not none or blah blah blah
is not false okay so we've been looping around and doing loops and loops of
loops we looked at the the indefinite loops the while loops that kind of run
for a while the definite loop and we looked at break and continue as a way to
either escape completely from the loop or go back up and discard the current
iteration of the loop we looked at none we looked at Boolean variables with four
loops definite loops where you've got some kind of a set or a list or a some
kind of sequence that you're looping through and then the concept of loop
idioms where you do something at the top something to each item and then some you
you sort of get a benefit at the bottom and and so that gets us through
iterations.